Hi everyone, welcome. Thanks for joining
us. My name is Robert. This is our Monae
and Impressionism program at the
fabulous Metropolitan Museum of Art in
New York. Thanks for being here.
My name is Robert. I'll be your host. A
little bit about myself, I'm Mie from
Detroit, Michigan. I was an art history
major at the University of Michigan
before transitioning off into the
business world. And I spent the first
two years of my career working at the
Detroit Institute of Arts. And my
favorite artist, not counting Claude
Monaet, I'll go with um Frederick
Remington. How about that? And we also
have our fabulous friend Patty joining
us. Hi Patty. How are you? And do you
have a favorite artist, not counting
Claude Monae?
Uh I'm very well today. And let's see. I
think after last weekend, I'd have to
still I'm still stuck on um Georgia
O'Keeffe.
Oh, okay. Well, that's cool. She's very
talented,
slightly.
And hi Brad, how are you? Thanks for
joining us. Where are you connecting
from? And do you have a favorite artist?
Hi Robert, this is Brad. I'm calling in
from uh Falling Waters, West Virginia.
And my favorite artist, I guess I'll
have to go with Andrew Wyth because um
Monae is really my favorite, but he he's
he's already taken by the program today.
Oh, I see. Okay, no problem. We should
do a we should do a program on the wives
because a very talented artistic family.
Yes.
And then Patty, you mentioned George
O'Keefe. So if anyone missed it, um we
had a program last weekend on George
O'Keeffe called Flowers and Abstractions
and I just posted on our YouTube channel
this morning. Sorry, I've been busy at
work, so it was a little bit delayed. So
you can check that out. Um and then
speaking of programs on YouTube, we've
actually done other Monae programs. So,
our first time we did a Monae program
featuring his artwork at a specific
museum was at the National Galler Art in
Washington DC and we went to the Art
Institute Chicago and talked about all
the Monae paintings there. And today
we're going to be talking about the
Metropolitan Museum of Art in New York.
If you want to watch these other two
programs, they're on our YouTube channel
which is called Washington DC History
and Culture. I'll send a link out for
that um later on as soon as I upload
this program. also.
All right, let's talk about Mr. Claude
Monae. He was born in Paris. A lot of
great artists that uh spend time in
Paris are not from there. Like for
instance, Vincent Van Go and Pablo
Picasso and various others. But Claude
Monae was actually born in Paris and he
spends the first few years of his life
there. He was born on November 14th of
1840.
And ironically enough, it was the same
year this famous print was made of
Paris. Now, if you're wondering, hey, if
that's Paris, where's the Eiffel Tower?
Well, they hadn't built the Eiffel Tower
in 1840. That would come a little bit
later. And then eventually,
the Monae family moves to northern
France in a place called La Hav. Claude
Monaet's father was a successful
businessman and he was in the maritime
merkantile business, meaning he sold
supplies and equipment to boats and
ships and things like that. Of course,
there's a lot more of those in northern
France along the coast than there are in
Paris. And so he moved the family
business.
And speaking of Monaet's parents, there
are the two of them.
That's a photo of Claude Monaet's father
and mother on the left. And then a
painting that Claude Monae did of his
father several years later.
Unfortunately, Claude Monaet's mom, who
he was very close to and was very
supportive of him, passed away when he
was a teenager. And Claude Monet and his
father did not have uh the best of
relationships. They did get along
sometimes, but uh it was a little bit
rocky also periodically because Claude
Monet's father wanted him Claude to take
over the family business and instead
Claude decided he was going to be an
artist which didn't sit well with his
father. Um and so they clashed
frequently on that especially because uh
during Monaet's early career he
struggled a lot financially and so it's
unfortunate he became Monae did um he
became a successful wealthy artist
during his own lifetime but
unfortunately his parents did not live
long enough to see that happen.
And who do you think this guy is?
It's actually Claude Monae as a young
man and he knew from his teenage years
he wanted to be an artist
and he pursued that with all of his
gusto so to speak. Um now for me
personally my opinion uh when people
think of Claude Monae they usually think
of flowers, gardens and landscape
paintings because these are amongst his
most well-known works. And while he did
paint many many paintings in these
subjects, he also did a lot of other
things. So we're going to see these
paintings today, but we're also going to
see things on various other subjects. So
you don't want to uh typ cast Claude
Monaet as just strictly a guy who made
paintings of flowers, gardens, and
landscapes because he did so many
different types of things including a
lot of paintings of architecture. He was
very fascinated by architecture which is
interesting contrast from landscapes and
gardens. He was also interested in
people. He does numerous portraits of
people throughout his career. Oftentimes
family members or friends that he was
close to.
He does a lot of paintings or did a lot
of paintings that have water in them. So
you should really be on the lookout for
this. I'd love to do a study to see what
percentage of the Claude Monet paintings
he made uh during his lifetime have
water in them because it's a really
large percent. So something for you to
be on the lookout for. And all these
paintings I'm showing you now, we'll
look at in more detail in just a little
bit. They're all in the collection of
the Metropolitan Museum of Art.
And let's go through Claude Monaet's
artwork in mostly a chronological order
so you can see how his style and artwork
changes and develops and evolves over
time. And as always, Brad and Patty,
feel free to chime in whenever you see
anything interesting or noteworthy. So,
let's talk about the early years of
Claude Monae.
And here is the earliest painting of his
that's at the Metropolitan Museum of Art
in New York. It was his family doctor.
and he painted this in 1864. Uh for
Americans joining us, that was the year
the Civil War was raging. Not that the
Civil War really has anything to do with
um Claude Monet, but just to give you
that historical context. And Claude
Monaet is known as the father of
impressionism.
However, um this painting was done well
before impressionism was invented, so to
speak. Impressionism comes along in like
the early 1870s.
And because this painting was done well
before that, it's considered a
pre-impressionist painting. And Claude
Monaet was 24 years old at this point in
time. And what was before impressionism?
Well, it was just the traditional art
style of the day. And so you see a lot
of artworks by Monae and others that
have kind of this dark earthtone
background and this kind of like single
source lighting with a solitary figure,
etc.
And like for instance, one of the most
famous paintings at the Met is this
portrait by Velasquez.
And if you've seen this before, it's one
of their well-known works museum. It's
not a French impressionist painting. I'm
just strictly showing it to you for
comparison and contrast purposes. So
this painting is from 1650. And then you
look at the Monae painting from several
years later and you can see a lot of
similarities. So early on, Monae, he's
making paintings in kind of a very
traditional style, so to speak.
Robert, is it fair to say that prior to
impressionism, it that landscape focus
painting was not particularly common?
Oh, um yeah, great point. Um sometimes
it is, sometimes it is. kind of depends
on the artist in the period. But yeah,
landscape painting oftentimes throughout
history has not been held in as high a
regard as some other um versions. Like
history painting um for most of history
up until the past say like uh 200 years
was always considered like oh the most
the best kind of artwork you could make.
U but yeah, landscape painting uh not
the greatest at that point in time.
The Hudson Valley School seems like a
notable exception to me. Is that
accurate?
Oh yeah. Yeah, that really um put things
on the map so to speak in America. And
then even the impressionists, they
really um changed the um the impact of
landscape painting just because they
were painting outdoors and they're doing
all these different landscape paintings.
So yeah, that's a great point. Um so you
don't really see um landscape paintings
throughout history consistently. You do
in different periods um but not
consistently throughout time. And then
speaking of landscapes, here's one that
Monaet did himself. This is a a forest
that was southwest or is that's still
there southwest of Paris. And so he does
this landscape and again it's kind of
very traditional style
done in 1865
and very nicely done but very different
than his later works which we'll see
shortly.
And then this is an unusual painting.
I'm guessing if you walked up to a bunch
of different people at the Met and asked
them who made this painting, if if they
weren't familiar with Claude Monae, uh
they wouldn't have guessed him. Um so
this is from the late 1860s. Again,
pre-impressionism,
but as he does throughout his career, he
features water in this painting.
And light. Yeah.
Yeah. And light. Yeah. Great point.
Thank you, Patty. I appreciate that.
Yeah. And light. You can always already
see um his early interest in depicting
light. The reasons why he liked water is
um for one thing he just always lived
near the water. So he either lived in
northern France along the channel or he
lived near the sand river. Um so that
was one reason why he liked it. Another
reason was because he liked how light
and water changed over time. And of
course if you have light shining on
water, it's constantly moving and he was
really fascinated by that. And of course
water is very beautiful. And so here's
some sailboats.
And I like to show these paintings just
because people might not have been
familiar with these um early works of
his, but it just kind of give you a
starting point. All right, so here's a
place in northern France called S Andre
and Monae ends up living near here. So
he grew up not far from here. This
particular city is traditionally been a
resort town and he ends up making a lot
of paintings here throughout his career
including these two which are really
considered uh masterpieces of Monaet's
early career. So let's take a look at
these two.
Here's the first one. This is a garden
scene and it's a garden along the
waterfront and you have some people here
and they're hanging out in the garden
and then off in the distance you can see
water and boats and things like that.
And so again, this is a seascape. It's
along the Normandy coast. It's a resort
area. Once again, we see water and Monae
like many of the impressionist painters
was really influenced by Japanese art.
And so you're so a show you a classic
example of perhaps the influence in just
one moment. But this is again really
considered one of Monaet's many
masterpieces. It's hard to say um which
painting of his is the most famous or
most important. Um there's a handful and
if you had to make a list, this one
would be on that list. And it's a really
beautifully done work. It's got great
light as Patty mentioned, beautiful
colors. Um, the people, the gardens, the
boats, the sky, just really kind of a
rainbow of all these different colors
and artistic effects taking place here.
And then if you want to know where this
geographic area is, so here's Paris and
here's London for our friends in
England. And then this is the Normandy
coast.
where the battle took place near S.
Andre.
Monae spent the summer of 1867 with his
family at S. Andre, a seaside resort
near Laav, which is where Monae spent
most of his childhood. It was there that
he painted this buoyant sunlit scene of
contemporary leisure, enlisting his
father, shown seated in a Panama hat,
and other relatives as models by
adopting an elevated viewpoint, which is
interesting in and of itself. The
painting, the terrace, sea, and sky as
three distinct bands of highkeyed color.
So here's the land, one band. Here's the
water, a second band. Here's the sky.
Three band. That's interesting. Um,
let's see. Monae emphasized the flat
surface of the canvas. His approach,
daring for its time, reflects his
admiration for Japanese prints.
And here's a famous Japanese print of
Mount Fuji
by the great artist Basai.
And if you look at this painting or
artwork, you have some people and
they're on a terrace and they're
overlooking the water and Mount Fuji off
in the distance.
And then here's the Monae painting. And
not that he's copying the Japanese work,
but people have often wondered, hm,
wonder if he got any inspiration um from
the print because Monae was very fond of
Japanese art. He had uh Japanese
artworks hanging in his house. Um and so
this was a very famous print. So some
people have wondered wonder if he got
any kind of inspiration or ideas. Now
they don't have anything that looks like
Mount Fuji in northern France, but they
have a lot of other cool stuff including
water and boats and all that um thing.
And then really interesting that his
father is included in the painting
because they had somewhat of a
challenging relationship.
Interesting, Robert, that both of them
incorporate a technique where it extend
elements of the lowest
uh level into the uppermost level. I
think it would entirely change the p the
painting if you didn't do that.
Yeah, it is it is really cool how it
also, you know, it has kind of the
elevated look and you're looking down
the horizon is far off in the distance.
Um, so I mean there's are other
paintings that kind of look like this,
but it is somewhat unique um to have
this type of setup.
And here you go.
And you have the Frenchricolor flag on
the right. People aren't quite sure what
the flag is on the left. Um, some people
What's that?
It looks like a nautical flag because
it's triangular.
Yeah. Yeah, that's a great point, Petty.
Um, that's what actually a lot of people
have theorized. might have something to
do with the boat off in the distance,
but I definitely think it would appear
much flatter if you didn't have that
lowest most ele uh element extended all
the way through the three layers.
Oh, yeah. Yeah, definitely.
And so, again, you see water over and
over again. So, if you were to see this
painting like hanging on the wall of a
museum, you might like, "Oh, wow. That's
really nice and beautiful." um and just
notice the water but not realize how
frequently he includes the water in his
artworks.
Someone's asking me about my
pronunciation. I American so I use the
American pronunciation. I don't use the
French pronunciation. So sorry if that
bothers someone. I don't I say Van Go
for instance. I don't say Van because
I'm not European. But if someone wants
to say pronounce it that way, that's
totally fine. Um, and again, you
frequently see flowers and gardens and
things in Monaet's paintings, including
the flowers here. So, nice, beautiful
garden. It looks like a nice place to
spend uh a nice sunny afternoon along
the water enjoying the flowers and the
company of the people and the water and
the boats off in the distance.
All right, so here you go. the early
years of
Claude Monae.
Petty and Brad, any other thoughts on
these early paintings?
No, I just um like I said, I'm kind of
fascinated with that idea because I
don't think I ever registered it before.
That idea of you of emphasizing the flat
canvas but also keeping the life in it
by extending one of the elements all the
way through.
Yeah. Because it's kind of unusual. I
mean, you see it sometimes. It's not
like it's completely um uncommon, but
it's kind of more uh frequent just to
see people using more of that what you'd
call it a traditional
um perspective type of thing.
Yeah.
What what drew your interest in um that
one? Anything in particular?
Um no, no. When you when you um
flashed the um that's not a nice word.
when you showed the picture of uh that
compared it to the Japanese scene that
was similar uh in terms of its setting
um it popped right out at me. I'm like,
"Oh, yeah. Both of them, even though the
flat canvas is the is the issue and
we're talking about the similarity of
the scene, I don't think either one of
them would be as um have as much impact
without that element that connects all
three together."
Yeah. And that is that is a great point.
It is a flat canvas, but yet wow, this
looks really three-dimensional, and you
know, it takes a lot of skill to be able
to make um that look realistic, so to
speak. So, good job, Mr. Monae.
Brad, any other thoughts from you?
Yeah, I was thinking of the one before
this, the the one of the sailboat, you
know, last last art thing we did with on
Remington, we were talking about his
ability to show the motion in the
horses.
Oh, yeah. This is a little bit
different. The motion of the waves and
the boats.
Well, yeah. He's got he's got the
three-dimensional waves of a sailboat
cutting through a fairly strong wind.
Mhm.
On this and he's done a really good job
with it.
Oh, you know, I didn't make that
connection with the horses, but um yeah,
you're right. It is interesting how he's
in capturing which not an easy thing to
do unless you're a talented artist. But
yeah, the boats definitely aren't
stationary. And then the waves look
pretty that looks like a pretty um
strong
breeze that day with the waves over
Yeah. Oh, yeah. Yeah, definitely. So,
all right. Well, thank you. Appreciate
that. Let's continue on.
All right. So, let's call these
paintings, I don't know,
pre-impressionism. He made these uh
shortly before Impressionism took hold.
And during this point in time in his
career, he's really experimenting with
different things and different styles.
Uh sometimes with friends of his, which
would also become famous artists.
And here are two well-known Monae works
that are kind of companion paintings.
One of them at the left is at the
Metropolitan Museum of Art in New York.
And the other one is at another one of
my favorite places, the Art Institute of
Chicago. So, same uh subject matter,
same location, same artist, um same time
frame, but just two different museums.
And so interesting kind of compare and
contrast between these two early
well-known Claude Monaet paintings. All
right, here you go. This is a riata
scene and it's another seascape along
the Normandy coast. Once again, water is
in the subject and of course there's the
Art Institute Chicago version.
And so again, this is a popular resort
area. A lot of wellto-do people have
vacationed here throughout the years,
including even into today. And again,
this is not far from where Monaet grew
up. Remember, he was born in Paris, but
um when he was a young boy, his family
moved to northern France. So, he was
very familiar with this area. He spends
a lot of time here throughout his life,
and he ends up painting scenes here on a
regular basis. And here was a letter he
wrote to one of his friends. Among the
seascapes, I am doing the regatas of Laa
with many figures on the beach and the
outer harbor covered with small sails.
And it's a really beautiful painting. I
love the uh combination of the water
with the cloudy sky and the boats and
the people and the sunshine and the
light. It's a great package of artistic
effects that he's included here.
And then just for a comparison and
contrast, here's the famous one that's
at the Art Institute Chicago.
And notice this one is very similar, but
also very different. It has a much
darker, cloudier sky
versus the more light filled one at the
Met.
And here they are side by side.
All the similarities. And yet there
there's no doubt possible that they're
two different temperatures.
Yeah. Yeah. The scene's very similar.
And um you know sometimes like for
myself when I see an artist, they've
made two um kind of similar paintings.
They're very very similar. It's like
okay. Yeah. Well, I could just look at
one of them and kind of get the idea.
But this one um they're very different.
Um the approach that he took and like
you were saying the climate and etc. So
well done.
And again, this is from 1867. Another
thing, too, is like if you're to look at
this, uh, where does your eye focus? For
most people, our vision tends to start
in the top left of something and kind of
work our way either down or across or
diagonally. Um, with this work, just
because there's so many things going on,
um, my eyes are kind of darting all over
the place. looking at the boats and the
people and the sky and the water. Um,
interesting in that regard. And then the
horizon line, we were talking before
about the other painting was somewhat
elevated. Uh, this one is a little bit
more of traditional. The horizon line is
where the sky
meets the land, so to speak.
And he devotes quite a bit of the
painting to the sky, which in and of
itself is interesting just because you
would think that traditionally the
people, the water, and the boats would
be like the main point of emphasis, but
yet um he's includes a large portion of
the painting is devoted to the sky and
the clouds, the all that kind of stuff.
So, kind of the horizon line is
something maybe you want to look at if
you're looking at paintings, uh, just
because it can kind of give you some
maybe interesting perspective on what
the artist was trying to focus on.
And Yeah. Yeah. So, he uses the
techniques of of um impressionism to
convey a really reality sense. There's a
lot of activity, a lot of life going on
in this.
Yeah. You can almost hear the
hear the activity taking place
and it's all interconnected. You've got
a village in the background. You've got
people using the water for water things.
Uh and of course shipping was very
important at that era. And you've also
got human beings that are uh a part of
the whole scene.
Oh yeah. I'd like to be here. I mean
this looks like a nice pleasant day
along the water.
And then here's a closeup of the people.
I always find it funny to look at these
historical artworks and see how um
well-dressed people are. You know, now
they'd have um you know, t-shirts and
cut off shorts and flip-flops and stuff.
Got women with dresses and parasols and
men with jackets and top hats.
Yeah, you definitely don't see people in
the water other than the people sort of
working with the boat, which that would
be launching a boat type of thing. Mhm.
Nobody recreating in the water,
right?
And there are the boats.
That could be a whole painting by
itself, but it wouldn't be quite as
exciting.
Yeah, it wouldn't be quite as um
intriguing and maybe wouldn't keep your
attention as long, but yeah, just I
could look at just this one uh by
itself.
And there you have it. So again, one of
the great um early paintings by Claude
Monae.
All right. So Claude Monae was friends
with many other artists, some of whom
became very famous, including Renoir. So
Monae and Renoir, uh they have a
long-term um relationship. There was a
time early in their career, they were
almost like brothers. That's how close
they were. And they spent a lot of time
talking about their ideas with art. They
both wanted to kind of change and shake
up the traditional establishment, so to
speak. Um, and they would frequently go
venture out to places together. And it's
really cool when the two of them uh
would make paintings of the same
subject. You can compare and contrast
it. So, kind of like how we just did the
compare and contrast on um two different
Monae paintings. How about we do uh the
same thing on two different paintings by
Claude Monaet of the same scene, but a
little bit different. So this also is
like another um resort kind of area
in the air and this is outside of Paris.
And this painting is at the National
Gallery in London for our friends in
England. This one's at the Met in New
York. And how this works is um there was
this kind of like um boat house and then
there was like a little island here and
they had a bridge and the land is over
here. So the bridge would extend out
from the land
across here to the little island and
then there'd be another short bridge to
the boat house. And over on here on the
right there'd be drinking and dining and
dancing and people talking and stuff
like that. So this is almost like a
panorama uh scene that he split up into
two different paintings.
So again, this one's at the National
Gallery in London
and here's the one at the Met. And one
of the things that Monae and the
Impressionists are really interested in
is kind of documenting the modern Paris
life, so to speak. We were talking
before about landscape paintings. Um,
prior to impressionism, history painting
was one of the big uh, genres where
people would do um, paintings from
stories from the Bible or Greek and
Roman mythology or important battles and
things like that. The impressionists
aren't interested in any of that stuff
for the most part, but they are really
interested in just kind of what's going
on in modern Paris, kind of like
everyday life. And so here is a scene of
dining and drinking and dancing and then
also uh people in the water with the
boating and the fishing and swimming and
all the other stuff that comes with
that. Here's actually an advertisement
for this spot. So you can see um here's
that island that I was referring to. And
then there was this um little bridge
kind of thing that went to this floating
kind of dock um that would have the
music and the dining, dancing and
drinking, all that stuff. And of course
there's people swimming and boating and
all that kind of stuff.
And then here's the one Monae painting.
There's no doubt. I mean, we were we
started off looking at the ocean side
ones. There's absolutely no doubt. And
yet he goes back and forth so fluidly
that this is either a pond or a river.
You can't necessarily tell which one.
It's more likely a river. But um
yeah, that is a good point. Like how I
agree. You can definitely tell that. But
like why can you tell that? I really
don't know.
And how and and the fact that he was
able to convey both so so fluidly and
and efficiently.
Yeah. I mean because the water's a
little calmer.
It's everything. It's it's the
entertainment going on. You wouldn't
have structures like that at an at a um
ocean shore because they can't really go
out into the water because of the waves.
Like a like a what do you call it? A
pier. But um that's completely
different.
Yeah. Oh yeah. Very very different.
Now, um you may have heard this uh term
where the the impressionist artists um
they're going out and they're painting
uh the works on site called plain air.
Um he didn't do that here. He basically
visited this place, made drawings and
sketches and they would take them back
to his studio um and do the works there.
So, while Monae does do a number of
paintings on site, this particular one,
just FYI, he didn't um paint this here,
but he is with his friend Renoir, and
they're documenting the Paris life. And
oh, by the way, Renoir made a same
painting of the same exact spot, which
is on the right. This is a from a museum
in Stockholm. So, here's the island
again with the bridges and the people
and the boats and then the kind of the
floating dock here. and kind of really
interesting compare and contrast between
the great friends Monae and Renoir. So
somebody earlier commented about the
uplo nature of um Georgia O'Keeffe's
flower paintings, the intimacy. That's
exactly what you see in the difference
here that the Renoir is just far more
intimate.
Oh, you know, good point. Yeah, you're
they have more of a close-up view,
but you got to think they're standing in
the same spot. I mean, maybe Monae or
maybe um Renoir claw crawled into one of
these boats to get a better vantage
point, but I kind of maybe picture the
two of them sitting or standing there
side by side, wouldn't you?
Yeah. Well, I mean, and Monet was also
very interested in things like trees,
and of course, there's a much more
expansive water here. It's you can tell
what Renoir is painting is water, but
that's not his focal point. And we've
talked a lot in the past about um you
know, Renoir tended to focus a lot more
on people.
Yeah, that is a good point. When you're
looking at a painting, you should kind
of think about that like, hey, what is
what is the focus of this? I mean, there
might be a lot of different things in a
painting or an artwork or even a
photograph, but what is the artist
really trying to get you to focus on?
Like what's the emphasis? So,
kudos to you, Peg. Good point.
Yeah. Monet has that series of popular
trees too, doesn't he?
Oh, yeah.
Yeah. We talk about that a little bit
later.
All of those things fascinated him.
Whereas Renoir was always he always
seems to have people involved in
whatever he's painting. They tend to
part of this of the importance of the
painting.
So here's the Monae one.
Here's the Renoir one.
There's a perfect example. See that? See
that uh whatever that square arrangement
is like to the right of the painting. If
you show them both side by side, it's in
both of them, but it looks completely
different.
Mhm.
Yeah. There's much more of an emphasis
on it over here.
See that on the right? It almost looks
like some sort of a gate if you just
look at that. Whereas in the Monet one,
it like fades into the
Oh, yeah. I see how that works in that
photo. Yeah. That painting. I mean,
where did this boat go that disappeared?
All right. So, this really cool um kind
of side by side. Monet visit. Monaet
traveled a lot. Um so, in an era before
airplanes, people didn't venture out um
as much from home as they do today, but
he actually was pretty well traveled.
And at one point in time in his life,
actually a couple different times, he
ends up visiting the Netherlands
and he paints some houses along a canal
with water once again. So again, this is
probably considered pre-impressionism,
but it's from the Netherlands and he
travels frequently through Europe.
Unfortunately, Monae never visited the
America. It would have been great if he
would have come to the United States,
but never made it there. Once again,
water is a subject. And here's a letter
he wrote to his friend Camille Pasaro,
another uh great friend of his and
fellow artist who also would become a
famous impressionist. There is superb
place for painting.
There are most amusing things
everywhere. Hundreds of windmills and
enchanting boats. Extremely friendly
Dutch.
One of our viewers just made a point um
that this being Van Go's home country.
None of Van Go's Netherlands paintings
look anything like this.
Oh yeah, that is a good point. He
focused on a lot of different types of
things. Not anything like this.
And you
and then this is an interesting work.
This is of his son Jean and was done in
1872.
Jean was the oldest of his two sons. And
interestingly enough, Claude Monaet, as
far as we know, never offered this
painting for sale. It was actually in
his bedroom when he died. Um, and you
know, they had photography at this point
in time in history. But, um, some people
have thought that maybe he had a lot of
sentimental attachment to this painting
because as far as they know, it was
never put up for sale. So, how about
that? And it's his son
riding on
the hobby horse.
before we separated hobby horses from
tricycles.
Yeah. When did that happen?
I have no idea. That's a subject for
another program.
Okay.
History and culture. It's the mystery of
separating hobby horses from triceps.
So, very nicely done.
If you go back, you'll see that um
Claude Monet had two sons and he passed
away in 1926. His oldest son passed away
in 1914. So, he actually outlived um his
oldest son and he actually also outlived
his first wife. We'll talk about that a
little bit later.
His younger son was the one that uh did
most of the preservation and museum
work, right?
Yeah. Yep. We're all indebted to him.
So, any thoughts on this collection of
pre-impressionism paintings, Patty or
Brad?
You can see the elements of of where he
would eventually be going kind of lining
up in these paintings.
Yeah, I I totally agree with you. It's
kind of that's why I like to look at
these uh early works, not just from him,
but from any artist. you can if you kind
of know where things head, you can kind
of like get a hint of things to come, so
to speak. What about you, Brad? Any
thoughts on the pre-impressionism
paintings? Yeah, I was especially
impressed with the comparison between
Renoir and and um
and Monae here because as everybody was
noting that Renoir really focused on the
people and maybe that tree was a little
more spectacular
otherwise I I'm really impressed with
his pre-impressionism work and of course
impressionism was what made him famous.
So,
and you also too, you kind of have to
wonder um okay, so these two guys,
Renoir and Monae, they end up becoming
famous art, how much did they influence
each other um and what kind of impact
did they have just because you you got
to think uh if you're an artist and you
get to spend time with Claude Monaet or
Pierre Goose Renoir that you know that's
got to be helpful for your career. Um,
so really cool that the two of them were
kind of um, you know, sharing ideas and
uh, critiquing each other's works and
things like that. So it had to be
beneficial for both of them because they
both ended up becoming great famous
artists.
And if they were standing right next to
next next to each other when they did
those paintings, that's really
fantastic.
Yeah, there's quite a few artworks in
history where some where two different
artists have made a depiction of the
same spot, but you know, it's oh, it was
many years later or a century later. The
fact that they were there at the same
time, that's really cool and unique.
Well, um something I'm not sure if
that's what you said, Brad, but um Monae
did become um famous and successful
mostly on the basis of his
impressionism. But wasn't he at least
somewhat wellknown and successful prior
to which gave him kind of the necessary
leave to go into um more experimental
painting?
Yeah, he did. Um so they were both
really starving artists at the time they
go back to painting. They were Oops.
Um, at the time they were making this
painting, they were both really starving
artists. Um, a little bit different
because Monae came from a very wealthy
family, although he was cut off from
them for the most part. Um, Renoir's
family wasn't as wealthy, but they were
more supportive of him. Uh, and there's
a funny story. when Monae and his first
wife had their first son, uh they lived
not far from Renoir and Renoir would
bring over like leftovers to the Mones
because he was really worried about
their son uh not having enough to eat. I
mean, it kind of shows you how close um
that they were. But yeah, the fact that
if you get more money coming in, it
allows you to maybe be a little bit more
experimental, so to speak. I also think
that um uh Renoir was a great portrait
painter and so he made um while he was
doing impressionist paintings um of
landscapes and flowers and things he was
really bringing in a lot of money um
early on his career as a portrait artist
and Monae was to a certain degree but
not um to the extent I mean I'm I'm
guessing if you had to pick a point in
time early in their careers Renoir was
actually bringing in more money a lot
more money than uh Monae was just
because of all his portraits that he
did. So, kind of interesting compare and
contrast between those two.
All right. Well, let's continue on. This
is probably the most famous uh Claude
Monaet impressionist painting from early
in his career. And for art historians,
they really kind of tend this to be
like, okay, this is really like the
first impressionist painting. Like there
were other works that were kind of going
in that direction. Uh but this is really
like the one that kind of flipped the
switch, so to speak. partially just
because um the term impressionism
actually came from this painting. Uh a
critic looked at it and said, "Oh,
that's not even a real painting. That's
just like an impression of a painting."
Uh and the name kind of stuck. And so
Monae is considered the father of
impressionism because number one, he
ends up making this painting, which is
kind of considered the first official
Impressionist painting. Number two, he's
very prolific. Um and he's also u really
influential early in the impressionist
movement. um versus say someone like Van
Gogh who also was really influential
with ec
down the road so to speak. So I just
wanted to include this one even though
it's not at the Met just so you can kind
of get a sense of how all this kind of
fits together. This is a beautiful
painting near the ocean that um I don't
know I I think I've talked to you guys
about the way the fog breathes here.
That's one of the most fascinating
things. And of course
your fog is in the morning. So yeah,
great impression of what seaside
sunrises are often like.
Oh yeah. Yeah. And once again, we're
seeing water in the painting. So again,
not a painting at the Met, but just want
to include it just because it's such an
important uh work. So from here on out,
we'll kind of consider the paintings
impressionist. And then here's another
person that Monae was friends with, the
great artist Manet. Um, and so Manet
visited Monae at his home one day and
his wife and son were just relaxing and
he's working on the garden. So this is
not a Monae, not a painting by Monae,
but it's a painting of Monae by Manet
that you can go see when you are at the
Met.
This is one of those first who's on
first presentations.
Yeah, exactly. Um, so Monae was friends
with Manet and Renoir and Pasaro and
Seaison and many of the other artists.
So I wanted to include this even though
it's not by Monae, it's by
Manet, but it includes Monae.
And a closeup of his wife and son.
He left the hobby horse behind and
hanging out with his mom.
This is the same sun that's depicted in
that um hilltop painting, right?
Oh, yeah. Yep. And then this is an
interesting uh noteworthy. This is the
only painting of Claude Monae gardening.
There's a lot of paintings of his garden
um and a lot of paintings of him doing
different things. This is the only
painting of him actually gardening.
Interesting enough.
All right, let's talk about early
impressionism.
And again, impressionism kind of gets
started around the early 1870s. Um, a
lot of people like it for a variety of
reasons. Number one, usually the
beautiful colors. Um, it's kind of the
early stages of abstract modern art
among other things. So, we'll look at
these three paintings
and these three and we'll kind of call
all of them early impressionism. All
right. So, here we go. This is his wife
Camille and she's front and center in
the painting on the left and she's over
on the left
of the painting, the right side
painting. And these are both paintings
that were done in Monaet's garden. So
Monaet is known for his garden at Ji. Um
that would be a real thing, but this is
many, many years earlier. Uh the Ji
garden wouldn't come till kind of like
the second half of his life. So this is
pre given
and this is Camille Monae on a garden
bench 1873. Again, there's people
depicted here and the gardens. Um I
really love the beautiful clothes that
they're all wearing. Um his wife is
beautifully dressed. You have this
gentleman with the top hat and the coat.
And then off in the distance you have
another beautifully dressed room with a
parasol.
And the thing that's unusual this one
though, it has kind of a contrasting
mood in my opinion. On the one hand, you
can see the beautiful gardens and the
flowers in the background. But when you
zoom in and look at Camille's face,
she's very sad. And there's a reason for
that is because her father had just
passed away. It's thought that um they
had come home from the funeral at this
point in time. So, you can see she has a
very sad look in their face. thought
that maybe perhaps uh the neighbor came
over to pay his condolences, perhaps
even to give her these flowers. Um it's
hard to see, but she's actually holding
um a piece of paper in her hand. And
then off in the distance, there's
another woman, the beautiful garden. So,
kind of an interesting contrast between
the the beautiful flowers and the
sunshine and the sad expression on his
wife's face. I kind of almost wonder if
she's like, "Hey, um, can we take a
break from the posing for the paintings?
My dad just died for God's sake."
Monet's wife, Camille, is as easily
identifiable here as the mounds of
geraniums in the garden of the couple's
home. The same is true of her smart
ensemble. The velvet and de outfit
closely resembles the look for spring.
1873 is advertised in Paris fashion
periodicals. At this point in time, um
Monae was bringing in a decent amount of
money. He wasn't wealthy, but he was at
least able to uh support himself and his
family. Um painted the year Camille's
father died, she telegraphed sadness
while holding a note in her gloved hand.
The top-headed gentleman, a neighbor,
has perhaps called to offer his
condolences in a consoling
bouquet.
And another thing too, this is the
Victorian era, so you don't really have
people smiling and laughing and carrying
on like they do now when you're posing
for photos or things like that. So,
another kind of reason why she would
maybe have more of a serious look.
Well, those uh dark circles around her
eyes though, leave no doubt.
Yeah, that helps kind of set the mood as
well. and just, you know, she kind of
looks like she's a little, I don't know,
annoyed or perturbed in my opinion.
Yes, Margaret's saying he got the
sorrow. Well, definitely.
Well, thank you. Appreciate that,
Margaret. And um yeah, so this is what's
funny about looking at artworks, like if
you were to look at this and see it on
the wall. Okay, this if you kind of know
the the backstory that her father had
just passed away um and she's usually
depicted, there are paintings of her
where she's smiling, but that's actually
not the case here. So interesting.
backstory on this one. And then here's
another work of her, although she's kind
of a secondary figure to the garden. So,
this is the house that they're running
in the background. And this is a place
called Arantoy. It's northwest of Paris.
Now, um it's really part of like a
suburb of Paris, like an outer suburb of
Paris. Um when the Mona were living
there though, it was kind of a separate
little small town um outside of Paris,
and this is where he's residing at the
time. Um, so here's their house in the
background and then this beautiful
garden and then here's his wife Camille
prior to urban sprawl.
Yeah, urban sprawl. Right. Exactly. So,
if you kind of look at this, you think,
well, gee, is this a landscape painting
of his garden? Is it a portrait of his
wife? Is it both? I don't know. And then
if you're interested, the uh flowers in
the center are holly hawks.
What's interesting in in among these
three, not so much the one with uh
Camille centered, but these other two
are that they definitely have elements
of pointalism, which I don't think
people necessarily associate with Monet.
Yeah. No, they sure don't. Um, and I'd
like to do a program onism someday. Just
haven't gotten to that just yet.
And again, a beautiful scene. There's a
um I used to work for the Detroit
Institute of Arts and they have a
similar painting. It's a horizontal work
though of his wife in their garden. I
should have um brought that in as a
compare and contrast, but maybe next
time. And then you zoom in on her.
She ended up being included in over 50
paintings that Claude Monae made
throughout his career. So, we've seen
two here.
I still like almost as much as flowers.
Right. Exactly.
And so there you go.
You can see that that slightly pontalous
look um on the with the one with
Camille, but it's nowhere near as
um as emphasized on the one is in the
one on the right. Even um I think you
showed um during the uh O'Keeffe
program, you had contrasted um one of
her flower still lives with a Van Go and
a Monet. Yeah. Uhhuh. Yep.
That Manet bouquet uh or arrangement um
definitely had a point pointless uh vibe
to it.
Oh yeah. And we're going to see that um
painting in just a little bit.
Oh, I'm questioning.
And then here's another scene from
Arjenttoy
Spring fruit trees in bloom from 1873.
And this is actually, ironically enough,
this is the first Monae painting that
the Metropolitan Museum of Art obtained
for their collection. And they did it
way back in 1926. So that was the year
Monae died. Um, so Monae was a
successful artist uh in his middle and
later years. In fact, in his later
years, he was extremely wealthy. Um but
there was a time when he was not doing
as well financially but um he was well
known and so kind of interesting that uh
they didn't acquire one of his I mean
the Mets um it's definitely the most
famous art museum in America and it's if
it's not the most famous art museum in
the world it's right up there with the
Lou. So interesting that it took him to
pass away before they acquired a
painting of his in their collection.
Oops, went the wrong way.
And so these flowering
trees in the spring bloom
and great colors. No water in this one
though. We're a little bit of a slump
seeing water, but we'll get back to it
shortly. And then here, the painting on
the right is pretty well known. Uh, but
the painting on the left is one of
Monaet's most famous works. That's hard
to categorize anything that way just
because he made so many famous works.
But the one on the left is really u
considered a masterpiece. Not that the
one on the right isn't, but just kind of
wanted to give you the comparing
contrast between um his works of Poppy
Fields. And so, as we were talking
before, here's his wife once again, the
son, and then there's a woman here kind
of maybe it might be her, but it's a
little bit uh impressionistic. Might be
a little bit hard to tell, but perhaps
her.
Well, there's another uh mother and
child further up the hill.
Oh, yeah. Right here. Yep.
Yeah. Who are these two people?
We don't know.
And then here's the one at the Met. And
I really like the colors on this
painting. Look at the rainbow of greens
and blues and reds and yellows and the
cloudy sky, the sunshine.
And yet each of the elements, other than
maybe the trees, you could say, is very
subtle, but together they're like
there's a super vibrancy to them. Yeah,
exactly. I would agree with that. So,
again, really beautiful work. So, again,
I don't mean to diminish this work um
because it is a great painting. It's a
well-known painting of his. Um it's just
the the one at the um Easy Dorsy is
extremely well known. Like they French
government made a stamp of this
particular painting.
Interesting. Not the one with the two of
them on the top of the hill.
Um well they made no they made a a stamp
of this painting which I get makes sense
because it's in the collection at the
museum Dorsy in Paris.
I see. Yes.
So
and close enough.
In this one the colors almost seem to be
in stripes whereas the other one it's
overtaking the field which is
Oh yeah, you're right. It
it almost seems like that that's what it
actually would be in the spring when the
poppies pop.
Mhm. When the poppies pop
or the um what are those those
if those are poppies or are they u
Oh yeah. No, these are poppies. Yeah,
because the paintings are called a poppy
field. But it kind of reminds me when we
were looking before of the two paintings
um sure of how they're both similar but
they're very very different.
Poppies were very widespread in Europe.
That's one of the reasons why they're
the symbol from uh World War I.
Yeah, the memory poppies.
And then
here's some more garden views
and painting on the right. A little get
together.
So, this is a landscape paint. This was
a um area in Paris.
And so at this point in time, Monae,
he's really traveling around the
different uh areas, mostly in northern
France, but not always. Um he does, even
though he does not live in Paris, he
spends a lot of time there. So this is a
garden in Paris and really great
depiction of light and color, which are
kind of two um things that you see over
and over again in Monaet paintings. He
was really fascinated by light and he
loved color. And so he's really
interested in how light changes and the
visual say interpretation of color.
And then here's another one. Same
location. This one a little bit more
little more Renoiresque in the sense
that he's focusing on the people a
little bit more than he did the other
one. And he's depicting this modern
urban life of, you know, people, middle
class people, upper middle class people
kind of enjoying the urban leisure, so
to speak.
Yeah, this was during the guilded age.
Um
so the bourgeoisi the the middle class
was I think this is the first experience
of middle class life.
Oh yeah. Yep.
So again, um it's always neat to me when
yeah, you look at one painting, it's
really nice, but when you can see two
that are um similar, uh kind of gives
you more of a broad perspective on the
artist and what they're trying to do.
And uh interesting that, you know, the
one on the left is horizontal, the one
on the right are vertical, the one on
the right has much more emphasis on the
people uh than the one on the left. But
also at the same time they're very um um
compatible with each other, complement
each other. Well,
Helen is making a comment that I think
comes up in every single Manet program
we do. I like how one can feel the
temperature and wind of that day. Light
go ahead. No, no,
that comes up in just about every single
Monet program we've done.
That is a great point. It's I mean you
have to feel like wow you could really
get a sense of what the um weather is
like when you're looking at a canvas
with paint on it. That's some real
talent that it takes to do that.
It gives an impression of the day.
Yeah, exactly. So again, these are kind
of early impressionist works. We saw
these three
and then we saw these three
and unfortunately
Camille Monae
passed away in 1879. She had a lot of
health issues and this really devastated
uh Claude Monae. She was with him from
early on in his career and she was very
supportive of him. I mean, she probably
could have complained a lot about how
early in their marriage they didn't have
any money. They he Monae was so broke
that he actually got evicted from places
that he lived at more than once. I think
like two or three times. Um, one time he
owed some a guy some rent and he offered
him his paintings, his compensation. The
guy essentially said, "Listen, Monae, I
don't want your stupid paintings. I just
want my money." Um, and then there was
another time he came home and all of his
stuff was essentially on the sidewalk.
He had been evicted. His stuff was all
moved. Um, so she stuck with him. Um,
and was very supportive of him. But then
eventually she ends up passing away. And
at this point in time in his career,
he's selling a few paintings, but he's
not doing you. He's not wealthy by any
means. Um, but when his wife died, he
was really devastated. In fact, he
actually um attempted suicide. He was so
distraught. Um but fortunately he was
not successful in that endeavor and then
he ended up uh continuing on. So it's
nice that they have two of the 50 plus
paintings of Camille although the one
that we saw with the woman in the poppy
field might be her also.
she um had a lot of health issues and
when she had her second child um she
didn't die from the birth of the second
child but her health really went
downhill um after that and she died I
think what less than a year after the
birth of her second son which leaves
Claude Monae a widowerower with two
small children to feed but life
continues on u so then he ends up moving
to a place called BTOY which is also
northwest of Paris and it's also along
the Sun River
and he ends up making a number of
paintings of the Sen at VToy. So, if
you're not familiar with France, uh I
hope I don't offend anybody in France,
but the Sen River is kind of like the
Mississippi River of France. Not
exactly, but it's like the main uh
river. It's really important throughout
history. It runs through Paris. And so
Monae ends up making numerous paintings
of the sand, including these ones when
he was living at the poet.
And he would end up living there for
three years. And I always wonder if he
had a strong attachment to this place,
not only because um it was beautiful and
it was along the water, but it was where
his wife was buried. Um she was buried
at the toy. And so he ends up making a
number of paintings here. You kind of
have to wonder if he was sentimental
about that
because he makes numerous paintings
within like a mile or a kilometer of
this um church where his wife is buried.
And even before she passed away, um they
would spend time here because he has
paintings of her like when they're out
on dates essentially uh before they were
married. So you kind of have to wonder
what the maybe psychological impact was
of him painting these scenes here over
and over again.
Uh yeah, people are com I was thinking
like melancholy and Helen saying
loneliness and uh um I forget what
somebody just before that used a good
word too. Hold on. Um
oh romanticize which melancholy isantic
type of
uh sentiment. Yeah.
You can see it, but the church in the
background is where his wife uh is
buried.
No people.
Oh, there's notably no people in these.
Even these people are very, very
indistinct.
Yeah. Very minimal.
Yeah.
But once again, water over and over and
over again in these different paintings.
And then um this what we were talking
about before where he's these still
life. So he has kind of an interesting
uh shift a little bit for a while in his
artistic career where he really kind of
spends uh more time doing indoor
paintings. You know, he's doing all
these landscapes and flowers and things
outdoors. And when his wife passed away,
which is uh another reason why people
maybe think he was seriously depressed,
including the fact that he attempted
suicide, he does all these painting
indoors. you kind of have to wonder like
geez was he so um you know exhausted and
tired that he didn't want to venture out
but he continues painting um but he
makes this whole series of these indoor
paintings with the year or so after his
wife passed away so this one is a still
life called apples and grapes and it was
painted within the year after his wife
passed
and then here's two beautiful flower
paintings that he did. The first one,
oh, first a quote. Here's a great quote
from Claude Monet. In his own words, I
perhaps owe having become a painter to
flowers. So, hey, if that's what he
think his artistic uh aspirations came
from, makes sense because you see
flowers over and over again in his
painting. So, a little bit of insight
there. And here's a beautiful painting
of sunflowers.
But again, it's an indoor work and he
does this. I'm showing you three
examples that are just at the Met.
There's many, many more of these indoor
paintings that he did uh the year or two
after his wife passed away. So, kind of
interesting in that regard. Not that he
didn't do these indoor still life at
other point in times in his career, but
he did like an overabundance of them um
at this point in time. So, really
interesting in that regard.
And there's a greater element of
darkness in these.
Yeah, they're not quite as cheery like,
you know, flower painting. I'm I'm not
saying it's uh depressing painting of
flowers, but this wasn't this wasn't to
me have that X factor that some of his
other works do. Now, maybe it's because
I'm overanalyzing because I know the
story uh that's taking place here, but
they're not quite as like vivid as some
of the other like floral paintings that
you see either from him or from other
people. Although this one I think is a
little more cheerier. But then also this
is quite a ways after his wife passed
away. So beautiful painting of
chrysanthemums and really talented to
kind of get the the flowers are
beautiful in themsel but really kind of
inh talented to be able to get the sheen
on the furniture here.
And again see light starting to come
back into it. Shadow light and shadow is
um a huge theme of if you're trying to
portray the effects of light.
Yeah. Making more of an appearance here.
An avid gardener, Monape threw some 20
floral still lives between 1873 and
1883, garnering both critical and
commercial success. This painting was
exhibited together with the museum's
bouquet of sunflowers at the gallery
Duran Rule. So this um gallery was owned
by a friend of Monet's and it's where
many of his paintings were sold. So if
you can imagine going to a art gallery
of Paris and seeing this painting and
say, "Oh, I like that. I think I'll take
it home and hang it in my living room or
my parlor or whatever.
Yeah, you get to in that one you get
this that impression of the dance of of
light and dark and different textures
and
Yeah, he's kind of getting back to his
Yeah, the table is very solid. The
flowers are very um romanticized.
And the shadow is undeniable.
And then here they are two side by side.
So one of the great things of the it for
a lot of great museums don't actually
have any Claude Monet paintings. Um and
it's incredible though the Met has so
many. And it's really also incredible
you can go and look at two paintings
like this side by side hanging on the
wall of the museum because you can't do
that at uh every art museum throughout
the world. But they have a big
collection of Mones and these are the
still lives. Any other thoughts on these
Brad or Patty?
Well, the one on the right, I mean, one
of the amazing things in that whole
shadow and light thing is the fact that
those two lowest uh crosanthemums are
also reflected in the surface of the
table they're on.
Oh, yeah. So
that's a little bit more uh difficult, I
would think, to accomplish than that big
solid vase. If Do you see what I'm
saying? The contrast between the
solidity of the vase and the flowers and
yet he's portraying the the reflection
of both of them. That was what I meant.
Reflection, not shadow.
Oh yeah, Ray, what about yourself?
Yeah, I agree with Patty on the
reflection on that. The chosanthemum is
really outstanding.
He's still got the shadow from the
sunflower, but nowhere near as much.
Yeah, there's less reflection in the
sunflower and the fruit.
And of course, the fruit the fruit's on
a towel, so any reflection from that
table is covered.
Well, here's a great point from Patricia
I never thought about. She said, "Yeah,
he's one another reason why he might be
painting these um indoor still lives.
He's at home minding the kids." Yeah,
that does make perfect sense because um
you know he does he needs to do that and
as the kids maybe get a little bit
older, they don't maybe require as much
um attention. So, you know, I never
thought about that, but yeah, that's a
good point.
Also, you're not going to have fresh
fruit and flowers in the winter, but we
all we haven't gotten to it yet, but we
know Mr. Monae and most of those other
artists weren't too crazy about being
outside when it was cold.
Yeah, they don't have Whole Foods yet,
so you can't just run down there and get
pomegranate whenever you want.
of his paintings indicate that he did he
was very affectionate with his children.
I remember talking to my mom um and she
was born in the 1930s about how yeah,
you know, for most of her life, you just
couldn't go down to the grocery store
365 days a year and buy some grapes
because they just weren't in season um
and not available. Um whereas like now
you can pretty much go get anything at
any point in time, whatever your fancy
is. So all right. Well, let's continue
on. Here's some So again, more paintings
of water. Uh Monet grew up as a teenager
in the Normandy coast. He would return
there frequently and make many, many
depictions of things there. So this is a
cabin. Unfortunately, the cabin's no
longer there. Um but this was a customs
cabin where they would, you know, put
customs on goods that were being
imported. It's along the Normandy coast
and once again water making an
appearance in the seascape.
And then this is a famous rock formation
in northern France. It's very
distinctive because it has this hole in
it.
And he ends up painting this numerous
times. And just so happens that two of
the many paintings he did of this spot
are in the collection at the Met. So
here it is in a photograph in more
recent times.
And you can see why that would get
someone's attention is a very unique
geographical feature
degenerating quite badly in modern
times.
Yeah.
Well, they have a few they have Yeah,
they have a few different um uh
outcroppings, I guess you would call
them, like this along coast,
but again, he's going back to Okay. the
light and the water and the color and
etc.
Just the sense of activity is different
from from much different from the
photograph.
Yeah. And you don't see really see uh
you don't see people in the bottom one
and the right one. I mean you do kind of
see the human element with the cabin and
the boats in the distance but you don't
see people playing a um prominent
saying the life of the water and the
formation. The photograph does not
convey that. Whereas the two paintings,
the formation, there is a sense of life
um in the in the two formation rock
formation paintings that is just not
there in the photograph. And you talk a
lot in your programs about why would you
still paint if you had photographs?
And then um as I mentioned, so he
traveled a lot for especially for
someone of his era. And so here was he
went uh the trip to the Italian Riviera.
And look at these two paintings
from his trip there. These are palm
trees.
And again, not typical of what you think
of when you say Riviera paintings,
right? Exactly. Uh yeah, I wouldn't if
if I had never seen this painting before
and had to guess where it was done at, I
wouldn't have guessed the Italian
Riviera. But, you know, that being said,
he's venturing out, trying different
things. Here's another one. This is a
Valley scene.
There's a similar painting to this one
at the Dallas Museum of Art for our
friends in Texas that may have seen
that.
Oh, somebody just said these are similar
to the uh Gaspay or reminiscent of the
Gaspay Peninsula in Canada. Exactly. Not
exactly your typical Italian Alps
painting.
All right. So, I guess um these two
paintings I would kind of just can't
really categorize them other than he's
making like a transition point at this
particular spot in his career. Up until
now, um we've seen a fair number of
people in his paintings now. We haven't
really seen a lot lately. But that being
said, if you think about all the works
we've seen um from the beginning with
the doctor, painting of his doctor uh up
until now, there's been a fair number of
his wife was a few of them and things
like that, but really this is amongst
the last paintings he made of a person.
This was actually one of his
stepdaughters. Um and so he's going to
transition. Not that he dislikes people,
but he's really just going to focus on
other things besides people. Um and this
one too is also interesting to me, but
it's getting much more abstract. like
you can kind of tell, okay, yeah, this
is water along the shore, but um it's
got to get a little more
impressionistic. Uh impressionism itself
is a little bit more um abstract, but
it's really kind of starting to go to a
whole another uh level here. So, he ends
up remarrying
um a young lady named Alice, and she has
an interesting story. Her husband was
actually a patron of Claude Monae. her
husband was a wealthy owner of a series
of department stores in France. And
because he had money, he actually bought
several Claude Monae paintings. Um, and
then uh around the time that Monaet's
wife died, Alice's husband, the
department store dude, he ran off and
left her. And she had several kids. She
had six kids or no, she had, let's see,
one, two, three, four. She had five
kids. Uh, or no, four kids. Sorry. Can't
remember how many she had. and he had
two. Um, so then when his wife died and
her husband left her, they ended up
forming a romantic relationship. Uh, and
it was kind of almost sort of like the
Brady Bunch and the merged families got
together and he was married to Alice for
an extended period of time. Um, but
again, you don't really see a lot of
paintings of people after this point in
time. Now, he ends up living and
painting to 1926. Um, this work is done
in 1887. um that's pretty much going to
be the end of people being depicted. And
even here, it's not just random people,
it's his stepdaughters. And uh two of
them were particularly interested in
artwork. And so here, this is at not at
the Met, but the other side of the
country at the LA County Museum of Art.
This is called In the Woods at Giver
Verie. Blanch at her easel and Suzanne
reading. So, Blanch and Suzanne,
stepdaughters of Mones.
And so, this is Claude Monae. This is
Alice,
the two Monae sons. And then Alice's
I believe she had five children. And
there's five people in the picture. Um,
and then this one is at the Met. This is
Suzanne the stroller from 1887.
And there's fewer portraits of people in
later years, but they have these two.
One at the Met, one at the LA Con Museum
of Art. And again, kind of interesting
compare and contrast these two.
Suzanne is the one that eventually
married his son.
Uh, yes, I believe so. Because somebody
had mentioned earlier that um although
the younger son gets a lot of credit for
doing all the arranging that she also
had a a lot to do with um the
memorialization of his work.
Oh yeah. Yeah. Definitely. Yeah. He got
a lot of help from his family um
especially later in his life when he was
his health was deteriorating.
I really like for a while she
Oh yeah. Yeah. Um but I really like this
painting a lot. got great colors and
it's a nice vertical depiction of her.
And then these are the rapids. This is a
location in central France. Once again,
water as a subject matter.
He had done other paintings that were
this abstract, but you're really going
to shift after this. It's really going
to move more abstract in my opinion. So,
you can be on the lookout for that. So
kind of a transitionary phase and then
all right speaking of abstract let's
look at these paintings of the sen and
notice okay here you can kind of get a
sense of okay it's the river and the
rapids and the rocky shore. When you get
to these ones though these are much more
abstract like you can maybe tell that
okay these are water scenes and there's
fog and winter weather and stuff like
that. You kind of have to process it for
a little bit longer um than you do the
earlier works. So this is called ice
flows. And um as Brad was mentioning
earlier, Claude Monet famously did not
like cold weather. And so you figure he
had to must have really liked this scene
to want to put on his coat and go out
there and do this painting.
And once again, water is the subject.
Here we are again along the sand 1897.
much more abstract than the earlier
works that we've seen.
And then here's another one, morning at
the end. So this particular one, he
wrote letters about how he used to get
up early in the morning, even before the
light came out. So he kind of gets set
up and get his canvas and his easel and
his brushes all ready to go. So that as
soon as the light uh appeared on the
horizon, he'd be all set and ready to
go. And so this one maybe not quite that
early in the morning. Um, but that being
said, it is a morning scene along the
San Ji.
My guess is actually that it's before
sunrise. It's the It's the sky as the
sun is just before it starts to pop over
the horizon.
Yeah, just before it's coming up. Uhhuh.
The trees are dark.
That bright. Yeah, the trees are dark.
It's not really that bright.
Patty, you've made interesting
commentary before about these uh this
era of his works. Any additional
thoughts on these? I went through these
a little bit fast because we have so
many um paintings to look at today, but
any thing jump out at you on these?
Well, he's positioned kind of like I am
a major um river at the ocean. And his
ability to depict this, it's almost like
the fog that you get at that kind of a
setting is alive. And I've described it
before as like a giant some giant being
that is literally slowly breathing in
and out because that's the way the fog
moves as though there's something alive
in it and it really does amazingly
affect the what you can see the shapes
and contours and it changes from second
to second. It it's a he really does a
great job um depicting both the morning
light on the water and the foggy the fog
effects. There are times I just go
outside just to be in that sense of the
breathing fog.
Oh yeah. Wow. That's neat.
There are people that literally strive
to take videos of it that convey it
well.
Uhhuh. Oh yeah. Well, that's cool. Um
but again, if you go back to these ones,
you know, these are both nice. These are
nice also, but in a different way. and
just how much more abstract they are um
than I mean we have seen abstraction in
Monet's work but not to this extent
before and you're going to see more and
more of this because to me um these
really kind of start to see hints of
where he's going to go um artistically
with his paintings of the garden at Xi
Bernie
and throughout his life you know you
have to remember Monae painted for
decades and he's experimenting
constantly with different types of
things and um different styles and
subjects and colors and things like
that. So, you really get a sense of that
here.
Brad, any thoughts on the send
paintings?
No, I'm looking at the fog with great
remembrances of my youth. But
Oh, yeah. Why is that?
Well, when lived in New England, we had
a lot of it in the morning.
Oh, I see. Okay. Well, that makes
down here when you get it, it's pea soup
and you don't go anywhere for a while.
It's very rare.
Yeah, that's interesting that the
certain areas have a unique relationship
with fog. Well, you're not on a coastal
area where river and ocean meet, are you
either?
No, I've got a big river very close to
me, but it's not one that it's a PTOIC.
The So, it's not the big mighty river
you see down in DC. It's a little
smaller, but it's still a good size.
I think that's part of what creates the
fog is the the differential between the
land, the uh river, and the ocean water.
It it's a huge temperature differential
happening all the time.
Yep. I think you're
Oh, I didn't know that. Okay. Well,
that's good. You were learning all kinds
of stuff today, not just art.
Patty, you have the Marramac going into
the Atlantic, right?
The Marramac is south of here, and this
is the Pascatiqua. Scott. Okay.
It's a huge river.
Yeah.
How do you spell that?
No, I'm just kidding.
UA,
I think.
Okay. Um, we've kind of seen this before
where Monae is doing these different
paintings of the same subject. Um, but
kind of on a limited basis. Later on his
career, he really gets into this where
he's fascinated by depicting the same
scene at different times of day. And I
don't just mean like, you know, two or
three paintings. I mean like dozens. Um
and he does that here with the
poppplers, the hay stacks and the Ruan
Cathedral. He also does it with the
train station in Paris. Although we
don't have a um example to that. So what
he's trying to do here, he's showing the
same subject but at different times of
the day, different seasons of the year
and different weather effects. We kind
of have seen him do that before.
Remember the paintings along the shore
or those ones we just saw at the send.
again not doing two or three paintings
like that but doing 15 20 25 30 um and
so this is why the poppplers the hay
stacks and the ruan cathedral paintings
are such well-known works by just
because he the volume of works that he
did um of these same subjects is really
incredible um so all right so this is a
funny story he um sees these popular
trees and now at this point in time
Monaet is living in gibrilly
garden yet. So he's doing paintings in
Giver, but not of the garden because the
garden doesn't exist at this point in
time. Um, so he's traveling around the
countryside looking at different things
and finding uh images or subject matter.
He ends up doing 24 of these popppler
paint the 24 paintings of these popular
trees. Now, funny story. He saw these
trees and thought they would make a
great set of paintings, but then he
discovers that some guy bought the trees
and was going to cut them down to use
the lumber. Oh my god. Oh no. And so he
went and gotten a hold of the guy that
bought the trees and basically rented
them from the guy like paid him money to
not cut them down until he was finished
with his paintings because at this point
in time um he's doing okay financially
and he has um the ability to do so. Just
so just the fact that he wanted to make
all these paintings before the uh trees
were cut down is interesting. Then I
always wonder like gee these these are
such famous paintings. Whatever happened
to the wood? Maybe it ended up being you
know furniture or components of
somebody's house or something like that.
But we'll probably
of furniture. Yes.
What's that? What's that Patty?
A series of furnishings. Yes.
Yeah. Oh yeah. Yeah. Well that's what
they would do now.
Exactly. Well, I was thinking the same
thing, rent a rent a view as opposed to
now you have all these zoning fights
about people wanting their view
preserved and you know somebody else
wants to sell the land and it's so just
the concept of rent a view is kind of
neat.
Oh yeah. But you know what happened to
this popppler wood that was taken from
these trees? We don't know. Um, so
here's the Met painting at the top. And
then just for kind of comparison and
contrast, here are some other popular
paintings that are from the series.
Again, he does 24 of the paintings of
the same subject. So you're seeing five
of the 24. And um, what I find
noteworthy is just the colors. Um,
notice the ones on like the left side
are much more lighter and brighter and
warmer. And the one on the right is much
more cooler um, and darker. And then the
one at the Met is kind of somewhat in
the middle. Like the foreground is kind
of coolish with the darker colors, but
the background um is more lighter. So
really interesting to kind of see uh him
doing this approach here.
And then another um thing about Monae,
he was really particular about his
perspective. Remember before we were
talking about like the elevated view um
and things like that. So here um he
wanted the scene to be from this exact
spot. And if he was on the opposite side
of the shore, he was too far away. And
so what he did is he got in a boat and
he would park the boat um in the river
so that he could get this exact vantage
point because if these he's on the
opposite bank, he's too far away. Uh if
he's right on the trees, he's too close.
But he has to be in this very particular
spot. And there's kind of numerous
stories of Monae during his career doing
this where he's got to be in this one
exact spot. He can't be a little bit
closer, a little bit further away, a
little bit to the left or the right. No,
he's got to be right here. And so you
see that um taking place here with the
boat.
Well, look at look at how essential that
ring of trees and to the uh left
background that shows up in every one of
these series. So it really has an impact
on how you see the poppplers.
Yeah. Oh yeah. And um also too, I mean
it really adds like another dimension to
the painting because if you go back to
this one, um which I like a lot. I
really like the colors in this one. It
doesn't have that element of the warmer,
lighter colors in the background. Um and
then these ones, uh they're all warmer
and lighter. So again, he's doing this
24 series of paintings, the same
subject. Um notice too, these are
vertical paintings. This one's more of a
square. Um so different kind of
perspectives in that regard. And that
ring of trees is almost like a super
highway in the background. But except it
has it does change with each season and
and with the light because they are
living trees.
So that that would be part of why his
perspective would be important. Imagine
if it was just those poppplers and not
the trees setting them off.
Yeah. It wouldn't be quite as um
visually interesting. And so yeah, if
you can This isn't the kind of boat that
he used. I just needed an image. But um
he had a bigger boat where he could put
like four or five canvases in it, paint
them. And so he would work on one for
like a few minutes and then the sun
would change and they would shift to
another one. Uh and then he's going
through this process and then he'd pack
them up and take them back to the
studio. And then I don't know the next
day or a few days later he'd bring
another batch out, work on them. So he's
working over these uh 24 paintings over
a period of several weeks and then
eventually the guy he finished his
painting and he let the guy cut the
trees down. Um so here's a similar thing
he's doing where uh same
idea where hey same um subject but
different times of day different seasons
of the year and different atmospheric
effects. So this is also done at Ji the
hay stacks um there's 25 paintings in
this one. Now this was a big financial
success for him because at this point in
time um he's doing well financially he's
not a million or anything but he's doing
well. The haystacks were a big hit and
he got so much money from selling these
haystack paintings, the series of them,
that it led to him purchasing the
property at Gibrin. Up until then, he
had been living there, renting it. Um,
so this was a very important set of
paintings, not only professionally um,
for Claude Monet, but personally as
well. Again, he doesn't like cold
weather. So, the fact that he's going
out here and venturing out in the cold
because he wants to have a depiction of
the hay stacks with the snow is
noteworthy. Again, very someone used a
good word, meticulous. That was from
Katherine. Thanks, Katherine. I
appreciate that. Between 1890 and 1891,
Monae devoted some 30 paintings to the
hay stacks in a field near his house at
Giver. He did 25 that were kind of in
the same style and then he did a handful
that were a little bit different, but
they kind of grouped together. Um,
sometimes in the midst of this effort,
he wrote to the critic Gustong Jeffrey,
I'm working very hard, struggling with a
series of different effects. hay stacks.
But at this season, the sun sets so fast
I cannot follow it because you know one
thing you have to keep in mind when
you're making an oil painting it takes a
long time. It's a very laborous process
and the sun's light is changing out of
it and that used to um frustrate and the
sun sets so fast I cannot follow. The
more I continue the more I see that a
great deal of work is necessary in order
to succeed in rendering what I seek. So
he's got this vision in his head. He's
trying to create it. Uh, hast stacks was
the first group of paintings that Monaet
exhibited as a series in 1891. 15 were
shown at the gallery Durant in Paris.
And then um the paintings are not
together for any of these series.
They're split up in museums all over the
um world. But if you want to see a bunch
of them put together, you should go to
the Art Institute of Chicago because
they have six haystack paintings all in
the same museum. Um, and so I just
wanted to give a shout out to our
friends in near Chicago.
And then here's
look at the length of the shadows,
especially in the one that's probably
autumn because I don't know if people
know, but like
at the winter solstice, your shadow is
the longest it's or tallest it's ever
going to be. And at the summer solstice,
it's the smallest. Look at that. You can
almost be certain that's late autumn.
That one up on the upper corner.
Yeah. Oh, yeah. Yeah. Great point. It's
just funny you mentioned that because
that's actually my favorite of these
six. Um, and then again, here's the one
at the Met
and zoom in a little bit closer
and full. Okay, so we saw the poplers,
we saw the hay stacks. We didn't get a
chance to talk about the um train
station in Paris just because they don't
have one of those paintings at the Met.
Um, but that also was a series. And this
is another series, the Rouan Cathedral.
Uh, he did this in 1894. It's a series
of 30 over 30 paintings. And remember,
Monae is really fascinated by
architecture. He's not just um
interested in landscapes and gardens.
And it's another great depiction of
light and color. And this one is also
another funny story of his being
meticulous. So here's the painting.
And it's a famous cathedral in France,
the Ruan Cathedral. Ruan is north of
Paris on the Sun River. And okay, the
Met one is on the top and then other
versions of this painting are on the
bottom row. So these are at different
museums throughout the world including
the National Gallery in London, the
National Gallery of Art in Washington DC
among others.
This one in my opinion a little bit more
these are a little bit more closer
together stylistically
um than the poppplers or the hay stacks,
but you maybe don't have the same
opinion.
And okay, so here's what Monae is trying
to accomplish. He's talking to a friend
in a letter he wrote about the impact of
light and color. Everything changes even
stone. So what he means by that is when
the light is shining on this cathedral,
uh it looks different. So the colors and
the light change of the cathedral and so
everything changes including the stone
which is noteworthy because you don't
really think of stone as changing but
the look of it does. And then here's the
cathedral itself. a good chance you
should visit this um site. It's a really
beautiful, fabulous and amazing
structure.
And then so Monae, he's trying to figure
out, remember, he's meticulous to use uh
the word from earlier. So he's trying to
figure out, okay, where am I going to
position myself for these all these
paintings I want to make? And so he's
walking around and he's like, okay,
well, there's these buildings. So this
is across the there's like a open
courtyard. So if you were to back up a
little bit and turn around in Ruan, this
is what you would see. So picture you're
facing this building and then um so say
this building that we're looking at is
like 12:00. Um the cathedral would be
like over at like say the equivalent of
like 5:00 if you know the hands on the
clock which you might do. But anyway, he
decides that the best position to be um
to make these paintings is inside this
building right here. If he's outside the
building, he's going to be too close.
Um, he doesn't want to be over here. He
doesn't want to be over. He wants to be
right inside the building. Uh, now the
issue was the building was the first
floor was being occupied by a woman's
lingerie shop. Uh, now though, this is a
big tourist center. So, if you come
visit here, uh, they have tourist
information that they hand out to
things. But anyway, he's like, "Oh, I I
want to be inside the building, but the
place where I want to be is a woman's
lingerie shop. So, what am I going to do
about that?" So, he ends up going to
talk to the proprietor of the woman's
lingerie shop, a woman. And, you know,
he explains who he is and what he's
trying to do. He's like, "Hey, can I
rent out like the corner of your shop
and set up a bunch of easels there so I
can make paintings at the cathedral?"
And I would have loved to hear that
conversation. Um, but he pays her and I
guess she says yes because he ends up
doing that. So, for several weeks, he's
kind of cordoned off this
this uh uh corner of this shop, this
front corner, and you know, there's
people in there going about their
business, and yet they got this guy over
here making these paintings at the
cathedral, which I don't know, me being
skeptical, I would have thought maybe
there was some other kind of weird thing
going on, but no, he really seriously
just wanted to be in this exact spot. He
didn't want to be up here or up here. He
needed to be down here. So, um, so that
being said, this is probably the most
famous set of paintings ever made in a
lingerie store. I don't know, maybe
there might be others that I don't know
about, uh, but I think these are the
most famous ones.
At least paint any of the ladies,
Robert.
Well, yeah, that's kind of like, hey,
well, you know, he was very focused.
He's not going to get distracted by the
women in the lingerie. Shows you how
meticulous and focused he is.
If you're shop owner, you're thinking of
this is Claude Monet. There might be a
mutual benefit here.
Yeah, exactly. And you know, notice he's
not doing uh paintings of women at this
point in time. He's just strictly
focused on the cathedral. So, he was
very uh very determined in that regard.
Didn't get distracted like like like
many men would. But that being said,
cathedral also referred to as she though
that aren't sure major cathedrals
considered more feminine than than
Oh, um you know, I don't know. That's a
good point. I never thought about uh
that or heard that. But yeah, you might
be right. Um
he's just painting different ladies.
Oh yeah.
And then um you know, again, one of the
things I wanted you to take away from
this program is just kind of how diverse
his subject matter was. You know, he
didn't just do flowers and gardens and
landscapes. He did, you know, people and
architecture and water and boats and all
this other stuff. And here's a great
quote that really kind of sums up his
approach to art. Every day I discover
more and more beautiful things. It's
enough to drive one mad. I have such a
desire to do everything. My head is
bursting with ideas. So, pretty cool
quote that kind of sums up uh what he
was trying to accomplish as an artist.
And again, these series, the Popular
series, the Haystack series, the Ruan
Cathedral series, or the Train Station
series. And while we've seen that
before, um, he really focused on this
for several years of his life. And then,
as I mentioned before, Monae likes to
travel. Uh, two of his favorite places
he visited was London, which he ended up
going to many, many times. And then he
made a visit to Venice. Um, now
unfortunately, he wasn't there in time
for the Jeff Bezos Lauren Sanchez
wedding, but that being said, he still
was able to make it there and check it
out in person. So, here you go. This is
another series. It's the houses of
parliament and he's doing the effect of
fog done in 1903 1904 and uh London was
a favorite place of Monae which is
interesting to me because the uh I'm an
American but it always seems like the
French and the British have kind of like
this rivalry. So interesting that a
Frenchman would be so fond of um uh
London but they they've really adopted
Monae. When you go to London, you
actually see a lot of Monae stuff um in
museums and in stores is because he was
so fond of the place. But he ends up
making over a hundred paintings while uh
during his different visits to London.
Again, there's the water being depicted
as a subject matter. And then he's
really fascinated by architecture. If
you're in London, you're going to be
visiting there and want to be in the
spot uh where Monae made these
paintings. He didn't go in the boat this
time. He determined that the uh vantage
point from St. Thomas Hospital uh which
is along the river would be adequate and
so he makes the paintings from there
and again pretty abstract. We kind of
saw him moving in that direction
earlier.
Helen just mentioned that um technically
he is catching the early stages of um
lethal smog.
Oh yeah.
Which did become a healthis. Yeah.
Yeah. I should have went to California
when I lived in Los Angeles.
Yeah. Not for him, but it did it
actually became um a hazardous situation
for Londoners for quite some time.
Oh yeah.
Part of the 20th century. Yeah.
And then um this building is officially
called the Houses of Parliament or the
Palace of Westminster, although uh
Americans and other tourists tend to
call it Big Ben, but Big Ben is really
just the the clock tower piece. Now,
this is a more recent photograph. I
didn't take this picture myself, but
okay. Okay, so here is this building.
It's a really incredible structure to
see up close in person. Um, it had only
been open for um, a few years when Monae
ends up painting. It wasn't like this
had been here for a hundred years
earlier. Um, and it's been a popular
tourist attraction ever since. But if
you look at this photo, like, okay, the
person here, they captured the whole
building, including the Big Ben on the
right. Um, and then here's another photo
from a different vantage point. Same
thing. Okay, they've got the whole
building. They even have the Big Ben
over on the right and the bridge and the
river. Now, if you look at Mo's painting
though, he doesn't have the whole
building. He only has the left side of
it. Now, why is that? Why wouldn't he
include all this other stuff? I'm just I
don't know for sure, but I'm guessing um
I think maybe he thought if he included
the Big Ben that would kind of distract
people because it might be because I'm
an American, but when I look at this
building, my eye always gravitates
towards that. And then also too, he's
not interested in depicting what this
building looks like per se. He's
interested in showing you how the light
uh interacts with the water and the
surface of the building and stuff. And
for that reason, he doesn't need to show
you the whole image the way a photograph
would. And you'll see this in his other
paintings as well, um that he did not
only this area, but also of Venice.
And so here's a similar one. This is in
Venice,
famous palace, and he did this in 1908.
So he visited Venice. It's another funny
story. He ends up visiting Venice with
his wife on vacation. Um, and he's not
planning on doing any painting there.
He's just planning on relaxing, enjoying
himself. But he was so aruck by the
beauty of Venice that he ends up making
uh 37 paintings while he's there. Most
of them again feature water but then
also architecture. You're not really
doing people per se.
And Venice has been a popular tourist
attraction for centuries.
Now Monet had to take the train there
because they didn't have uh that whole
airplane flight thing at that point in
time.
And so here's the building that he
depicted. It's the palace on the right.
He's really kind of not included the
tower that goes with it again. Maybe.
Well, it is there, but it's very
indistinct.
See it way over on the left.
Yeah. Right. It's very kind of subdued.
You don't say, "Oh, tower." It's sort of
just there,
but again fog.
And so, yeah, you can see why Mr. Bezos
chose this for his wedding location.
Beautiful area. And um there's it's
really we don't have time, but it's
really neat to look at these Monae
Venice paintings. They're um uh I really
love Venice and love Monae and to see
him doing the depictions of the city. Uh
really amazing.
And again, here's more of a what it
looks like from a postcard type of
picture
versus the Monae scene.
Yeah, this one the one on the left would
be more of a traalog poster.
Yeah,
the one is like I was here.
And then here's a great quote from Monae
on Venice. It's so beautiful. I console
myself with the thought of returning
next year for I was only able to make
attempts beginning. So, he planned on
coming back to Venice um but he never
was able to do so. He only makes the one
trip. But if you go back here, he did
end up spending several weeks there
between October and December of 1908.
But yeah, he he talked about Venice and
letters he wrote to his friends uh back
in France and then when he got home,
you're like, "Oh, wow. This place was so
amazing." But uh like happens sometimes
in life uh he was not able to make a
return visit. So you go somewhere, you
got to enjoy it while you can because
might not be able to revisit again.
some of these quotes along with the
paintings he he strikes me now they have
a name for it it's called highly
sensitive persons um but some of these
you can feel that ache to be able to
express everything he's experiencing I
bet you he was one of those highly
sensitive persons
oh I see that's neat I never thought
about that but yeah you can kind of tell
he's a sensitive guy like yeah I went to
Venice and drank a couple beers and it
was pretty cool you tell he's much more
of a sensitive introspective kind of
person read these letters kind of same
thing with Van Go and his letters
and yeah it affects them physically
so yeah trips to and you remember before
we saw him visiting the Italian Riviera
saw him visiting Netherlands he's doing
these paintings all over different parts
of France so a welltraveled guy
and then all right let's talk about Gibr
the home stretch of our program got a
little bit more to go um so okay so he
ends up moving to Ji Bernie. He rents
the house initially, but then he ends up
uh getting enough money to be able to
purchase it. He ends up building this
fabulous water lily garden, which
becomes the subject matter of many of
his later works. Notice there's no
people whatsoever in any of these
paintings, although you do see the
bridge on the top left. And so, okay,
we've seen all these great Monae
paintings. Which artwork did he consider
to be his masterpiece? And if you've
seen my program before, you know the
answer to this because I always think
it's fascinating.
He said his masterpiece was not a
painting. It was actually his garden at
Gibr. So Monae was a very accomplished
gardener in addition to being talented
painter and he considered his garden to
be his masterpiece. Imagine that.
And here is the garden. So he didn't do
the heavy labor, so to speak, of the
garden, but he did spend a fair amount
of time being kind of like the visionary
of this. He did have assistance with the
planning of it, mlaying out of it, and
of course the actual manual labor to
build this. Um, but this is really his
vision. And for uh people that are
really into gardening, the garden at Xi
Bernie uh is really considered one of
the top gardens in the whole world,
which is amazing when you consider he
wasn't a professional gardener per se.
Even the pond was created. Is that
accurate?
Yeah. Yeah.
It a naturally existing pond body of
water.
Yeah. No, it didn't naturally exist
there. So, he bought this property and
end up creating this. And um it's funny
because I was reading a review of it
many years ago before co and some guy
wrote something like, "Yeah, my wife
dragged me here and I'm not even into
gardening or Monae, but that was really
cool to see his garden."
So he ends up making and then one of the
reasons why he made it you know he loved
nature and plants and all that stuff and
he really wanted a place particularly as
he got older that he could kind of uh
you know stay and have subject matter
for great artwork that was close to home
because uh Monaet is a a fascinating
individual on the one hand he did love
to travel and he goes to all these
different places but he also was kind of
a homebody. I mean his favorite thing to
do was really just to stay home with his
friends and family and make paintings.
Um and so when he sets up the garden
here, he has all this great subject
matter without leaving um the comforts
of home, so to speak. So this is one of
the most uh famous later works. It's
another series. He did a whole set of
paintings on the bridge uh the Japanese
foot bridge of the garden at Giver. This
is from 1899. Again, water making
another appearance.
Isabelle just said a great thing. Um his
paintings are an homage to his
masterpiece. I love that one. That is a
great
Thank you, Isabelle.
I should include that in here. Thank
you. I appreciate that. Um here's a
photo of him
um on the bridge. It's a colorized
photo. It was initially a black and
white photo. And then here's the museum
card of this painting that you can read
if you go visit in person. In 1893,
Monae, a passionate horiculturist,
remember he had those paintings of his
wife um in their garden at his previous
home, purchased land with a pond near
his property in Giver, intending to
build something, quote, for the pleasure
of my eye and also for the motives to
paint. End quote. The result was his
water lily garden. In 1899, he began a
series of 18 views of the wooden fick
bridge over the pond, completing 12
paintings, including the present one
that summer. The vertical format of this
picture, unusual in this series, most of
them are horizontal or square, give
prominence to the waterlies and their
reflections on the pond.
The other thing I love about this series
is the other reflection he includes is
the bridge.
He loves the bridge.
Yeah, you can tell he was really uh
proud of this bridge, which hey, it's a
cool bridge and he should be proud. Um,
I used to live in Washington DC, spent a
lot of time at the National Galler Art.
This is a similar painting that they had
done around the same time, the Japanese
foot bridge. Notice this one is a square
painting though. The other one we saw
was a rectangle that was vertical.
I think all but one or two of them have
the reflection of the bridge though.
Yeah. And so it's really fascinating
that he's including that um here. And
also too later on he eventually um so
it's like he's infatuated with this
bridge because he keeps paying it over
and over again. But then at some point
in time he's like okay yeah been there
done that and doesn't include it
anymore.
But it kind of uh agrees with Isabelle's
quote about an homage to his
masterpiece.
Yeah I love that. Thank you. That was
very cool.
And then these paintings as they get
later in his career now notice. Okay, so
this is painted 1914 to 1917. He passed
away in 1926. Later on his life, he
starts having health issues of various
types including cataracts. Um, so I
guess to me it's not surprising that the
work becomes a little bit more abstract
because his vision is deteriorating. But
I believe even if he wasn't having
vision problems, he his artwork would
have became more abstract on its own
anyway just because that was kind of the
direction that he was going. So kind of
the in my opinion uh the two things kind
of merged together. But this is the path
through the irises.
No doubt. The path you take to the water
lily pond.
One of those unanswerable mysteries.
What's that?
One of those unanswerable mysteries. A
chicken egg question. Yeah.
Oh, yeah. Exactly. Abstract.
Yeah.
Um, let's see. Okay, then here's another
one. The water. I love the colors on
this. The blues and the greens, the
purples. This is from 1916 1917. Again,
water featured one more time.
And then here's a photo of the garden.
And I love the reflection of the water.
You can't see the bridge in this one
with the clouds. Um, and then the
waterlies themselves. this really unique
uh combination of all these different
things taking place with the water and
the liies and the light and the
reflection, all those different things
combined together. And then here is a
painting from 1919. Now look at this.
He's born in 1840.
This is done in 199. So he's 79 years
old. I mean, and this is an era when
people didn't normally live anywhere
close to that age. So he really lived a
long life
and he was a dedicated smoker.
Yeah. Yeah. Exactly. Maybe he would have
lived longer uh without that. But again
um the painting in comparison with the
photograph and you can kind of see like
oh okay yeah I can see what he was
trying to accomplish here.
One of Monaet's critics described this
canvas of 1919 as waterlies in full
flower asserting themselves, their
golden discs encased in purple against
the cloudy water. I like that's a nice
quote, but I like those better.
I'm going to replace this that this one
with her. Uh although the almost
80-year-old artist was reluctant to part
with recent paintings, he made this
landscape and three related pictures
with an eye to the market uh meaning to
sell. uh telling his dealers Gaston and
Jos Vernham that he was quote working on
them passionately. The Burnham brothers
quickly purchased the quartet.
What did you say to that about that
quote, Robert? It I couldn't quite make
Oh, I said I said I like this quote, but
I like Isabelle's quote from earlier,
but
Oh, okay. Gotcha. All right. Yeah. And a
lot of people if if you don't know um
waterlies are in fact related
in the same family as lotus. So there's
like a an eastern connection there too
that that are considered very meditative
and restorative.
Ah I didn't know that. That's a um
interesting play on this is he was
really fascinated by the Japanese and
Asian things.
Yeah. And Helen also called floating
liies. Yeah.
Floating liies. Mhm. So Brad and Patty,
any final thoughts on the Giver
paintings?
And we're actually getting the home
stretch, so any any thoughts on just
Monae in general and or the Giver paint?
Well, I love the the inclusion of the
reflection of the clouds, but it for
some reason I it just thoroughly
enchants me. It tells me something about
him that he does the reflection of the
bridge.
It's like it's definitely an intimacy
with his creation here.
So, kind of a funny but also sad story.
So, I used to um live in Washington DC
and I used to give tours at the National
Gallery of Art and one day this woman
came in and I was talking to one of the
security guards that I got to know there
and this woman comes in uh an Asian
woman and she's looking like really
distraught and behind the security
guard, uh are you okay? Can I help you?
And she's like, where's the um the Monae
painting of the bridge? And he's like,
oh, it just um shipped out two weeks
ago. was on loan to another museum and
the one was like, "Oh my god, I'm here
on vacation from Japan. I'm only here
for a week. This was like the number one
painting I wanted to see in your
collection." I was like, "Oh god,
sorry." So,
blessing trips.
Yeah. So, she was she was um visiting
Japan uh break from school and really
wanted to see this Monaet painting of
the water lily bridge, the Ashley
Gallery Art, but unfortunately it was um
it was on loan to another museum. So
anyway, kind of a funny sad story, but
um Brad, any final thoughts on the
paintings or Claude Monet in general?
That last story sums it up because I a
lot of people would be looking for that
bridge at a logo for for the Ji series.
Yeah, I saw this woman and I thought,
did she lose like her phone or a child?
I mean, she looked really distraught and
she'sing around because if you go to the
National Guy Art website, the um their
website will tell you like what gallery
the paintings are in. And
yeah,
but you know, they do loan out works or
they put them in conservation or yeah,
looking at her like, "Oh my god, what's
wrong with this young lady?" And then
when he started talking like, "Oh god."
So anyway, and I don't think
there are like there are exhibits from
time to time that borrow from other
collections, too. Yeah, that's why if
you really have your heart set on seeing
one particular work, you um you got to
go you gotta check to make sure it's
there. Although they had a lot of other
cool stuff. So,
a lot of famous artworks get loaned out
like when we had the um world stair in
New York. They brought articles from
Italy and all over the world.
Mona Lisa
there. They
Oh, yeah. The Mona Lisa when it came to
America back in the 60s. Yeah.
La talk came a lot of things came. I
mean
that the Isabella Stewart Gardner um
because they had she had the only
Tishon. It was from the mythology series
um that was in America and they did a
special exhibit. They brought the other
three from that mythology series. The
one that lives in America is uh the rape
of Europa.
Yeah. Yeah. That's a great thing. But um
I mean yeah it's a good thing when you
can go see um other works at uh you know
museums close to your house but that
it's always tough when a favorite uh
ends up leaving. Um and then Monae ended
up passing away. He lived a long way.
Born in 1840, passed away in 1926, but
that was a really long time for someone
uh born in 1840. And then if you're in
New York City, so we saw 40 Monae
paintings at the Metropolitan Museum of
Art, but if you're in New York, you can
go see 10 more because the Museum of
Modern Art has five Monae paintings. The
Brooklyn Museum has three Monae
paintings. The Guggenheim has one. Frick
also have one. So you can see 50 Monae
paintings in New York City. So how about
that?
And then so again,
grave is the same. Do you know if his
grave is at Ji or is it with his wife?
Oh um good question. Yeah so his grave
along with his second wife is at Janei
the church there which is not far from
his home. So yeah his um first wife is
buried at the other place and Monae and
his second wife are buried here.
Yeah friend Monet.
Oh yeah. Yeah. Mhm. I forgot to mention
that. Thank you. Appreciate that. Um
let's see. And then yeah, if you go back
so wow, we really covered a lot of
artwork looking at these 40 paintings.
But here was the early years
and then we the pre-impressionism.
The early impressionism.
More early impressionism.
What an extraordinary career.
Yeah, really amazing. The toy. This is
where the first wife is buried.
The still life's after she passed away,
Normandy,
Italian Riviera.
That looks like the Gaspay Peninsula
transitions, for lack of a better word.
The sun
the series poppplers hast stacks in the
ruan cathedral
London and Venice
and giver. So again really wanted you to
take away like wow yeah this guy did a
lot of different types of stuff it
wasn't just flowers and gardens and
landscapes and um you know these are
just the paintings at the Met. If you
were to do a similar view of other Monae
paintings at other collection, you
really get a appreciation for just how
diverse of interests he had uh in
depicting different things. Even though
he's he's he kind of reminds you of like
an actor or an actress that is in a
handful of movies that people kind of uh
you know associate with but then don't
realize like the full body of their
their work so to speak. So um uh we'll
wrap things up in just a little bit but
Brad and Patty any final thoughts on
Claude Monet before we call it a day?
Well, your description of of um his
career I made me think of like Angela
Lansbury, Maggie Smith, you know, those
people. It's like they played very
different roles throughout their careers
and they progressed as they aged, but
the average person would tend to know
only whatever their contemporary period
was. They wouldn't really realize how
different um those actors and actresses
had been. Um so that's
Oh yeah, go ahead. Sorry, I didn't you
No, go ahead.
Oh, no. I was just gonna say, yeah, it
reminds me of like Gene Hackman when he
just passed away. They Oh, the French
Connection and all this Mississippi
Burning, but you know, he was really in
all these really amazing movies. Uh, and
a few of them I'd actually forgotten
about until they were doing like the
retrospect of his life and kind of
waiting. I mean, one of Angela
Lansbury's earliest movies, she was kind
of um a shady character in Gaslight
and um but yet years later she's
portraying this nice old lady that
solves mysteries and it's like, whoa,
okay. You know, they transition a great
deal.
Uhhuh.
Oh, yeah. Brad, what about yourself? Any
final thoughts on Cla before we call it
a day?
No, I think that this this has really
been a good summary of what we've got
here and he he's he's obviously
progressed through his career and
invented a whole art form of
impressionism along with his colleagues.
It's his works are just phenomenal. This
this Italian Riviera on the right almost
looks like the Dolommites.
I didn't make that connection, but yeah,
you're right. But yeah, that's why it's
neat to look at a set of paintings like
this just because you get more of
appreciation for their range, so to
speak. What was that, Patty? Uh well,
one thing I'm curious about, I know
you've done a great program on um the
actual property at Jivier and is that on
um the YouTube channel, too, because
several people have
Yeah. No, I didn't I didn't record that
yet, but I was going to do it at some
point in time in the near future. So,
yeah, we do like a virtual tour of the
property at Jane, both the inside of the
house, the outside, but yeah, we need to
do that again. We haven't haven't done
that one a while.
Yeah, stay tuned, folks. So, we'll get
to that one, too, cuz it's interesting
to see the the uh connection between his
actual life and how he depicted it in
the paintings.
Oh, yeah. Yeah. No. Um definitely agree
with you on that. Um so, hey, if you're
in New York City or going to be visiting
and you want to see like a similar
program for other artists at the Met,
this is actually the fourth one we've
done on impressionism at the Met. So,
the first one was Manet. Gosh, I think
we did that like three years ago if I'm
not mistaken. Then we did Dega and
Renoir and then the Monae one. So, these
three are all on our YouTube channel and
then this one I'm recording today. I'll
put it on there. Um it might take me a
few days though because I'm super busy
at work, but I'll get it posted there.
When as soon as it's posted, um I'll
send out the link. So, if you want to
see more of the um impressionism
collection at the Met, we'll do that
soon. And then for the let's see for the
anniversary of the Declaration of
Independence, I'm doing a series next
year on the American collection at the
Met, but that'll be a little ways away.
And then if you want more about Monae,
this is the third of the series we've
done at Monaet at different museums. So
we did one just like this at the
National Guy Art in Washington DC. Um
and then let's see, last year we did
Monae at the Art Institute of Chicago
and then today's one is at the Met. So
there's three of those for you.
And then here are some of the paintings
by Monae at the National Guy Art. One of
my favorite places.
Oh yeah, there's the one on the hilltop
that everybody can feel the air.
Yeah, the bottom left. And then here's
another one. Monae paintings at the Art
locations. Yes.
So they have a lot more Monae paintings
than just these six at the National Guy
Art and more than just these six art in
Chicago. just to give you a sense of uh
what those look like. But again, you can
find on our YouTube channel. I'll email
out the link and the MET one becomes
available. And our YouTube channel is
called Washington DC History and
Culture. Thank you for all of the people
that have viewed our programs. 1.3
million people. Very flattering. And oh,
by the way, my mom thinks that's really
cool. So, thank you very much.
And then here's a
my son who was so softspoken when he was
younger talking for these people. And
then um here's my favorite quote by
Claude Monaet. Everyone discusses my art
and pretends or tries to understand
especially that Robert Kellerman.
If it were even necessary to understand
when all that is real and necessary is
just to love. So great Monae quote that
really kind of sums up the essence of
what he's all about. And then um just
FYI, some future programs we have coming
up if you're watching us live. Um let's
see, I guess this is two weeks from now.
We're doing a encore of our George Caleb
Bingham program. Uh he was a great
American artist. So on Friday evening,
June July 11th, we watching a film about
Bingham. And then on Saturday, July
12th, we watch having a lecture like
this about his career. And then I used
to work at the Detroit Institute of
Arts. They have a fabulous collection
including this great John Singer
Sergeant painting uh which is a kind of
a complimentary work to Madame X if
you're familiar with that painting. And
we'll be talking about their American
collection u Thursday evening, July
12th. And for our friends in New
England, we did this program a long time
ago, right when CO started, but I've
been kind of tinkering with it and I
finally have it to a point where it's
finished. At some point in time in the
next um few days, we'll have the date
for our Museum of Fine Arts Boston
Impressionism Collection program. You
can be on the lookout for that.
For the sake of clarity, Robert, you
have um Saturday, July.
Oh, no. These are the same dates. Oh,
sorry. This is a This must be the wrong
date. I think it's like the 20. It's the
20some. So, whatever. See, it must be It
must be the 24th. Sorry about that.
Yeah, the 11th would be Friday because
the 4th is on Friday.
Yeah. Yeah. So, sorry about that. Um,
but yeah. And then, um, Patty, are you
familiar with the collection at the
Museum of Fine? I mean, I know you're
not in the same state, but it is a New
England place, and I've heard you
reference the museum before. I mean, I
know you talk about the Isabella Stewart
Gardener.
Yeah, I've I've spent a lot of time
there. I haven't been there recently.
I'm getting older. Robert,
I don't it's not as fun a fun idea for
me to, you know, go through all the
effort to get to some of these places
sometimes and then do the museum itself.
But, um, yeah, it's it's a great museum.
I mean, I used to go all the time on
the, you know, how some museums have,
um, you know, the the free late day or
evening
the free date. Mhm.
Yeah. I used to go a lot just for that
because But it it's impossible. I mean,
it's one of those museums you have to
visit more than one time and know what
you want to see on that visit, you know.
Oh, I see. Oh, wait. No, on this slide,
the dates correct.
When did that happen?
I didn't even know.
Oh, did you change it?
I fixed it. Thursday, July 4th. But
yeah. Um, so some things coming soon, so
hopefully we'll see you then. All right.
Well, that concludes our program. Thanks
so much for joining us. If you're
interested, I'll play a preview of our
George Caleb Bingham program. He was
known as a Missouri artist. Uh, thank
everyone for joining us, especially
Patty and Brad for sharing your time and
expertise with us. So, thanks everyone.
Have a great day and we'll see you next
time.
Thank you. Thank